<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>y.tsutsumi.io - books</title><link href="./" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://y.tsutsumi.io/feeds/books.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>./</id><updated>2018-04-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Book Report: The Whole Brain Child</title><link href="book-report-the-whole-brain-child.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Yusuke Tsutsumi</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-04-22:book-report-the-whole-brain-child.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.amazon.com/Whole-Brain-Child-Revolutionary-Strategies-Developing/dp/0553386697"&gt;The Whole Brain Child&lt;/a&gt; discusses strategies to teach children how to deal with difficult situations in an empathetic and rational way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the focus on teaching children, the book included a lot of great insights for adults as well. In general, it is a great guidebook on how to deal …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.amazon.com/Whole-Brain-Child-Revolutionary-Strategies-Developing/dp/0553386697"&gt;The Whole Brain Child&lt;/a&gt; discusses strategies to teach children how to deal with difficult situations in an empathetic and rational way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the focus on teaching children, the book included a lot of great insights for adults as well. In general, it is a great guidebook on how to deal with emotional situations, and how to ensure that the approach is one that accounts for the impact on others and their well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general structure is emphasizing a few key strategies when encountering an emotional and upset child. Here is my interpretation of the general ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="introspect-when-encountering-conflict"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introspect when Encountering Conflict&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book posits that we have two different &amp;quot;brains&amp;quot; that work in tandem when encountering a difficult situation: the &amp;quot;lizard brain&amp;quot; which reacts with strong emotional responses, and the &amp;quot;upstairs brain&amp;quot; which can approach the situation rationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the theme of educating children on how to cope in situations of conflict, the book explains that, to best help someone understand the situation, it is first better to empathize with how the chid is feeling. Once the lizard brain is no longer in control, deconstruct the situation rationally. This quiets the immediate reaction of the lizard brain, and enables a discussion when your child is using their upstairs brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example: if your child is throwing a tantrum because they are not getting the ice cream they wanted, it is first best to acknowledge the feelings of the child first (&amp;quot;you seem angry&amp;quot;), then rationally explain that eating too much ice cream is not a good choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lessons works great for children, but I see it as a great lesson for conflicts with adults: if you want to reach an agreement with someone and you have a strong emotional reaction, first acknowledge the emotions, then reconcile on a logical level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="physical-activities-to-clear-your-mind"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Physical Activities to Clear Your Mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book references a study that explains that physical activities can help calm emotional reactions, and bring someone into the state to discuss the situation rationally. Thus, a good tool may be to help pace the room, or do some jumping jacks, before diving into the conflict itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="talking-through-the-situation-repeatedly"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Talking Through the Situation Repeatedly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one encounters a traumatising situation, and one that is difficult to understand (like a loved one being taken away by an ambulance, or a car accident), an insecurity can linger: one may become more upset when a loved one leaves for work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The insecurity stems from a lack of understanding, and the reassurance that, despite how traumatising the situation was, everyone still turned out ok. Talking it through multiple times, ensuring that the child has a good understand of what actually occurred during the scary part of the experience, and a reminder that the child is still ok at the end, will reduce that insecurity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="thinking-about-the-larger-picture"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thinking About the Larger Picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a conflict occurs, one can get invested and extremely emotional. This can occur with even small conflicts that have a minimal impact on our day to day lives, such as an argument at work. In those situations, the lizard brain takes over, and one does not weigh the argument appropriately. One often becomes invested and very upset if the outcome does not go their way (e.g. a minor technical disagreement at work).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a situation like this, taking a step back, and considering the larger impact works well. Will this choice cause me to lose my job? Will it cause my company to lose a significant amount of cash? Will I be the one responsible if things go wrong? If the answer to the above is no, then it is a sign that it may not be worth the investment, or at least being emotional about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find myself in this situation often: I am opinionated about many aspects of my job, and the company I work for. It is valuable to have a logical argument for what you are advocating, and to spend time on that. However, it does not mean that, if the outcome is to move forward with a different approach, I should be upset for hours or days afterward. The impact this decision will have on the part of life I care about is minimal. Keeping perspective on what is important helps focus me on the discussions I should be having, and spending more time on those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="use-introspection-to-understand-emotions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use Introspection to Understand Emotions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major theme of the book is examing the situation in a rational light, allowing some time to consider whether the response is appropriate. Being able to explain why you feel a specific way is powerful: you can better understand why you react this way, and modify your behavior if it is appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="explaining-how-others-are-feeling"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Explaining How Others are Feeling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children often act without regard to how others feel, such as grabbing a toy from another's hand, or erasing another's work. When a child does so, it is often without malice, but rather the lack of understanding of how it feels to have that done to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By explaining how one feels in that situation, the child learns how to empathize. Getting the child into the habit of considering other's feeling before taking an action helps reduce interpersonal conflicts, and can often avoid them. Deliberately educating on why one should feel empathy on a situation when the opportunity arises ensures the lesson is learned, and allows the child to achieve competency in a valuable skill early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="final-thoughts"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, &amp;quot;The Whole Brain Child&amp;quot; did a great job of putting more abstract ideas in my head in writing. I use many of the techniques outlined in the book when encountering conflict, but I had never put deep consideration into why those techniques worked. I have also never thought deeply about how to share these skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book does a great job at all of the above: it provides a step by step guide for moving from an emotional state of mind to a logical one, adding understanding of the situation to analyze what could be improved, and explains how to further build an empathic foundation in children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely recommmend a read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="books"></category><category term="book-report"></category></entry><entry><title>Book Report: The Millionaire Next Door</title><link href="book-report-the-millionaire-next-door.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Yusuke Tsutsumi</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-02-20:book-report-the-millionaire-next-door.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.amazon.com/Millionaire-Next-Door-Surprising-Americas/dp/1589795474"&gt;The Millionaire Next Door&lt;/a&gt; is a explanation of the behavior and attributes of those who have achieved a significant amount of wealth. Contrary to the title, it does not just examine millionaires: instead, it looks at those who have a significant amount of net worth, multiple times their income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-much-net-worth-should-you-have"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How …&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.amazon.com/Millionaire-Next-Door-Surprising-Americas/dp/1589795474"&gt;The Millionaire Next Door&lt;/a&gt; is a explanation of the behavior and attributes of those who have achieved a significant amount of wealth. Contrary to the title, it does not just examine millionaires: instead, it looks at those who have a significant amount of net worth, multiple times their income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-much-net-worth-should-you-have"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Much Net Worth Should You Have?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main gauge for determining your success is your net worth relative to income. The equation looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
2 * income * age_in_years / 10&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you are 40 years old and you earn 80,000 dollars, then you should have 2 * 80k * 40 / 10 = 640k of net worth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2 at the beginning of the equation is a multiplier factor that helps puts you in one of a few categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0.5: UAW (under accumulator of wealth). Anything at or below this number is the last quartile of net worth of those with similar income.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1: AAW (average accumulator of net worth).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2: PAW (prodigiuos accumulator of net worth): Anyone at or above this number is within the top quartile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book was written a few years ago (1996), so it could be that these numbers have changed. But the general philosophy is to set a goal of net worth that is a multiplier of your income, in contrast to a set number for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-behavior-of-the-wealthy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Behavior of the Wealthy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book contends that the wealthy have two primary behaviors in common:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;living considerably below their means&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;making sound, non-taxable investments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing a lifestyle that's below one's means results in a significant amount of excess income. That excess income can then be used to fund investments, which compount in interest and have returns that increase exponentially as time allow. The investment being untaxable (or taxed minimally) increases the return of the gains (as there is less money pulled out of the investment pool) in contrast to an investment taxed at normal income levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By building a foundation of net worth that compounds, and reducing the cost of living in one's day-to-day life, it tackles the goal of financial independence on both sides: reducing the target goal, and investing heavily to get to that target quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-spending-habits-of-the-wealthy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Spending Habits of the Wealthy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A majority of the wealthy interviewed had very similar behaviors around money. Oftentimes, the wealthy went with financially conservative options. This includes buying and keeping a car for decades, forgoing the finer things like exotic vacations and boats, and simple, cost effective hobbies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wealthy also strictly budget: they track spending closely to ensure that the wealth accumulates over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="thoughts"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this book formalizes a lot of the ideas we understand in principle. Many of the ideas the book puts forth are logical, but it is nice to have them all in one place. The book has already influenced the way I am organizing my assets. I am looking toward investing more, and setting a clear budget goal on the amount I would like to invest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the PAW target also helps, as it sets expectations on how much one should be saving, to continue toward the path of achieving a significant amount of wealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, I do not agree with the idea that we should live a frugal lifestyle and ignore the opportunity for unique experiences: vacations to new places and trying new things is a pillar of a satisfying life. Ultimately, wealth should be accumulated to enrich the lives of those you care about. Wealth does not accomplish that by sitting in a bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I aim to be more conservative around luxury items like products I do not need, or eating out when I can bring food from home. But I will continue to look for ways to use my wealth to get the most out of life, and I won't hesitate to take a step back from my long-term wealth goal to have a once-in-a-lifetime experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="books"></category><category term="book-report"></category></entry></feed>