<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>y.tsutsumi.io - languages</title><link href="./" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://y.tsutsumi.io/feeds/languages.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>./</id><updated>2015-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>How I Learn More Vocabulary</title><link href="how-i-learn-more-vocabulary.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-10-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Yusuke Tsutsumi</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-10-14:how-i-learn-more-vocabulary.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to reaching language proficiency, vocabulary is
important. To reach proficiency as &lt;cite&gt;quickly&lt;/cite&gt; as possible, the &lt;cite&gt;choice&lt;/cite&gt; of
vocabulary is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to explain my approach a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-to-learn-vocabulary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How To Learn Vocabulary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vocabulary from a spoken standpoint requires quick recall without a
reference, which is really only …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to reaching language proficiency, vocabulary is
important. To reach proficiency as &lt;cite&gt;quickly&lt;/cite&gt; as possible, the &lt;cite&gt;choice&lt;/cite&gt; of
vocabulary is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to explain my approach a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-to-learn-vocabulary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How To Learn Vocabulary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vocabulary from a spoken standpoint requires quick recall without a
reference, which is really only attained by practicing the same exact
things over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use flash cards, because they're the most
straightforward review method. I have two flash cards per word, one
testing translating from the language, and another translating to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anki is a great choice for any flash card learning, because it stores
your data about what you've learned, and modifies the frequency of the
cards accordingly: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ankisrs.net/"&gt;http://ankisrs.net/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the medium, the real challenge is investing the time and
effort. It's very easy to stop once you're a week in, or a month
in. In order to minimize this risk, vocabulary needs to be a routine:
it must be a part of one's daily schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I've made my commute to and from work into review time for my
language flash cards. I listen to the same playlist (something with no
vocals), start up Anki, and get to work until I've reviewed them
all. I've been doing it with German for over a year (roughly 30
minutes per weekday), and I've learned about 800 words completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Per word, it's taken me 7500 (~50 weeks * 5 days * 30 minutes a day) /
800 ~= 10 minutes a word. Not bad (although some are easier than
others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-vocabulary-to-learn"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What Vocabulary to Learn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timothy Ferris has &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2009/01/20/learning-language/"&gt;a great blog post&lt;/a&gt; about
learning languages (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2014/03/21/how-to-learn-a-foreign-language-2/"&gt;a couple&lt;/a&gt;,
actually) where he talks about finding the most frequently used words
and learning those first. It's a statistical method that is the best value for
your time in terms of vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any given language, a Google search will probably find a list
somewhere. In the case of Japanese In the case of Japanese, there's a
great post showing the most common terms used:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pomax.nihongoresources.com/index.php?entry=1222520260"&gt;http://pomax.nihongoresources.com/index.php?entry=1222520260&lt;/a&gt;. Even if
you don't understand the grammar at all, the vocabulary alone helps
you get a great context on a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's worth emphasizing the distinction between spokend and written
word frequency. My suggestion would be start with spoken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My suggestion would be to learn the first 100 or 200 words. This
provides a solid base of roughly one half of all spoken words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="where-to-find-more-vocab"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where to Find More Vocab&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you have a good base set of words, I would move on to learning
vocab that really interests you. Find a book, tv show, or game that is
available in your target language, and add any vocab you don't know
into the flash cards as you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I wanted to learn German.  Luckily, I love video games, a
medium that fairly often has spoken dialog and text. I found a game
I've wanted to play for a while, converted all text and audio to
German, and started it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as I encountered a word I didn't know, I paused the game,
wrote up a flash card, and continued to play.  As soon as I reached
100 new words, I stopped playing the game; I was only allowed to
resume when I had finished learning all my outstanding vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning of this process was incredibly painful: I would play for
maybe half an hour before I had over one hundred words to cover! But
as time passed, I learned more, and the game began to move a bit more
quickly. I also sometimes found places in the game where I was unable
to pause. In that case, I used youtube videos of others playing the
game to supplement: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=let%27s+play+deutsch"&gt;let's plays in German&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Japanese, if you like video games you're there: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://store.steampowered.com/search/?snr=1_4_4__12&amp;amp;term=#sort_by=_ASC&amp;amp;supportedlang=japanese&amp;amp;page=1"&gt;there are lots&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/292120/?snr=1_7_15__13"&gt;of
Japanese&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/8870/?snr=1_7_7_230_150_3"&gt;video games with full audio.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you prefer TV or movies, I'd suggest a website like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.crunchyroll.com/videos/drama"&gt;Crunchyroll&lt;/a&gt; or Netflix. I think
Japanese comics (Manga) is also a very good choice: unfortunately it's
not available readily online. However, I've found that buying whole
series' from EBay to be a straightforward process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="languages"></category><category term="languages"></category></entry><entry><title>Hacking Language Learning</title><link href="hacking-language-learning.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Yusuke Tsutsumi</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-09-03:hacking-language-learning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a disclaimer: I'm not a teacher, and I have no
experience in teaching languages. I've been trying to learn quite a
few though. Everything stated here is in my own, anecdotal case study
opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the goal is some level or proficiency, I feel like the standard …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a disclaimer: I'm not a teacher, and I have no
experience in teaching languages. I've been trying to learn quite a
few though. Everything stated here is in my own, anecdotal case study
opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the goal is some level or proficiency, I feel like the standard courses
don't accomplish that. Almost everyone I've talked to has started
learning a language in either primary or secondary education, but very few have
retained enough to continue to be proficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post marks the start of my journey toward a reproducible
curriculum that will produce language proficient individuals. I define
one as proficient in a language when:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one can listen (if applicable) to a conversation in a target
language at the speed natives speak, and understand the majority of the content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one can read and write in the target language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one makes grammatical mistakes 1% of the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one can speak in the target language, with a pronunciation that's
understandable by a native speaker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing as the US Department of State has their own &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://careers.state.gov/gateway/lang_prof_def.html"&gt;definition&lt;/a&gt;, I would put
my goal at a 3: minimal professional proficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's some of the things I think are worth being a primary focus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="making-language-practice-a-habit"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making Language Practice A Habit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond all else, languages require a very large time investment, over
a long period of time. Memorization is a huge part of learning
languages: two thousand words is probably around the bare minimum to
hold a free-form conversation in a language. Memorization comes with
practice and repetition. In order for someone to keep their language
proficiency, languages must practiced routinely: in other words,
language practice must be a habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="useful-from-day-one"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Useful from Day One&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning a language comes with the steep learning curve: There is a
lot of knowledge to absorb, and the usefulness of that knowledge
increases exponentially near the end, but is very slow in the
beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here would be to teach the material in a way where value is
maximized near the beginning. A high initial reward helps build a
habit that will take a student to language proficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="next-steps"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm bilingual in Japanese and English, so I will be using Japanese as
my test language for a lot of my teaching experiments. If you're
interested, please follow my blog by subscribing to the RSS
feeds. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="languages"></category><category term="languages"></category></entry></feed>